Fifty years ago in the old Soviet Union,
منذ خمسون عام في الإتحاد السوفيتي القديم
a team of engineers was secretly moving a large object
كان فريق من المهندسين ينقلون بسرية جسما كبيرا
through a desolate countryside.
عبر الريف المهجور
With it, they were hoping to capture the minds of people everywhere
بها، كانوا يأملون سلب عقول البشر في كل مكان
by being the first to conquer outer space.
بأن يكونوا أول من فتح الفضاء
The rocket was huge.
الصاروخ كان ضخما
And packed in its nose was a silver ball
حشي في أنفه كرة فضية
with two radios inside.
بداخلها راديو
On October 4, 1957, they launched their rocket.
في الرابع من أكتوبر 1957 أطلقوا صاروخهم
One of the Russian scientists wrote at the time:
كتب أحد العلماء الروس حينها
"We are about to create a new planet
نحن على وشك صنع كوكب جديد
that we will call Sputnik.
والذي سنسميه سبوتنك
In the olden days, explorers
في الأيام الخوالي، المستكشفين
like Vasco da Gama and Columbus
مثل فاسكو دا جاما وكولومباس
had the good fortune to open up the terrestrial globe.
حالفهم الحظ لفتح الكرة الأرضية
Now we have the good fortune to open up space.
الآن حالفنا الحظ لفتح الفضاء
And it is for those in the future to envy us our joy."
سيغبطنا على ذلك من يأتون فب المستقبل
You're watching snippets from "Sputnik," my fifth documentary feature,
تشاهدون قصاصات من "سبوتنك"، فلمي الوثائقي الخامس
which is just about completed.
والذي أوشك على الإكتمال
It tells the story of Sputnik,
إنه يحكي قصة سبوتنك
and the story of what happened to America as a result.
وقصة ما حدث في أمريكا نتيجة لذلك
For days after the launch,
لأيام بعد الإطلاق
Sputnik was a wonderful curiosity.
سبوتنك كان تحفة لافتة للنظر
A man-made moon visible by ordinary citizens,
قمر من صنع البشر يمكن للمواطن العادي رؤيته
it inspired awe and pride
أوحت الرعب والفخر
that humans had finally launched an object into space.
بأن البشر قد أطلقوا أخيرا جسما إلى الفضاء
But just three days later, on a day they called Red Monday,
ولكن بعد ثلاث أيام فقط، في يوم سمي الإثنين الأحمر
the media and the politicians told us,
قال لنا الصحفيين والسياسيين
and we believed, that Sputnik was proof
وصدقناهم، أن سبوتنك دليل على
that our enemy had beaten us
أن عدونا قد سبقنا
in science and technology,
في العلوم والتقنية
and that they could now attack us with hydrogen bombs,
وأنهم الآن قادرين على مهاجمتنا بالقنابل الهيدروجينية
using their Sputnik rocket as an IBM missile.
بإستخدام صواريخ سبوتنك
All hell broke loose.
فقامت الدنيا ولم تقعد
Sputnik quickly became one of the three great shocks to hit America --
سبوتنك أصبح سريعا أحد الصدمات الثلاثة التي أصابت أمريكا
historians say the equal of Pearl Harbor or 9/11.
يقول المؤرخين أنها تعادل بيرل هاربور و11 سبتمبر
It provoked the missile gap.
أثارت فجوة الصواريخ
It exploded an arms race.
فجر سباق السلاح
It began the space race.
بدأ سباق الفضاء
Within a year, Congress funded huge weapons increases,
خلال عام، مول الكونجرس زيادات سلاح ضخمة
and we went from 1,200 nuclear weapons
وصعدنا من 1,200 سلاح نووي
to 20,000.
إلى 20,000
And the reactions to Sputnik went far beyond weapons increases.
وقد ذهبت ردة الفعل أبعد بكثير من زيادة السلاح
For example, some here will remember
فمثلا، البعض هنا يذكر
this day, June 1958,
هذا اليوم، يونيو 1958
the National Civil Defense Drill,
تجريب الدفاع المدني الوطني
where tens of millions of people in 78 cities went underground.
حيث توجه عشرات الملايين من الناس في 78 مدينة تحت الأرض
Or the Gallup Poll that showed that seven in 10 Americans
أو إستطلاع الرئي الذي أظهر أن سبعة من كل 10 أمريكان
believed that a nuclear war would happen,
يعتقدون أن حربا نووية ستبدأ
and that at least 50 percent of our population
وأن 50% على الأقل من السكان
was going to be killed.
سيقتلون
But Sputnik provoked wonderful changes as well.
ولكن سبوتنك إستثار تغيرات رائعة كذلك
For example, some in this room went to school on scholarship
فمثلا، البعض في هذه الغرفة ذهب إلى المدرسة بمنحة
because of Sputnik.
بسبب سبوتنك
Support for engineering, math and science --
دعم الهندسة، الرياضيات والعلوم
education in general -- boomed.
التعليم عموما -- تفجر
And Vint Cerf points out that Sputnik
ويوضح فينت سيرف أن سبوتنك
led directly to ARPA, and the Internet,
قاد مباشرة وكالة مشاريع البحوث المتقدمة، والإنترنت
and, of course, NASA.
وبالطبع ناسا
My feature documentary shows how a free society
يوضح فلمي الوثائقي كيف يمكن لمجتمع حر
can be stampeded by those who know how to use media.
أن يقاد عن طريق من يعرفون إستخدام الإعلام
But it also shows how we can turn
ولكنه أيضا يوضح كيف يمكننا أن نحول
what appears at first to be a bad situation,
ما يبدو في البداية كوضع سيء
into something that was overall very good for America.
إلى شيء هو في مجمله جيدا جدا لأمريكا
"Sputnik" will soon be released.
"سبوتنك" سيصدر قريبا
In closing, I would like to take a moment to thank
في الختام، أود أخذ دقيقة لشكر
one of my investors:
أحد المستثمرين
longtime TEDster, Jay Walker.
من رواد تيد القداما، جاي والكر
And I'd like to thank you all.
وأود أن أشكركم جميعا
(Applause).
(تصفيق)
Thank you, Chris.
شكرا، كريس